Let’s say you’re trying to
find some solid information
about a serious health
problem that concerns you,
like high blood pressure,
or diabetes.
Yet, everywhere you look,
someone’s trying to sell you
something like vitamins,
yoga mats, blenders, drugs.
Well, breathe a
sigh of relief
because all we bring
you are the facts.
Welcome to the
Nutrition Facts Podcast,
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
Did you know that healthy
plant-based diets appear to
not only reduce the risk
of severe COVID-19,
but the risk of getting
infected in the first place,
even independent
of comorbidities.
Here’s our first story.
What’s the role of nutrition for both
preventing and beating COVID-19?
Nutrition-related myths
on protection and treatment
have been widely
prevalent in this pandemic,
and while there is no diet
that completely prevents infection
there are certainly dietary steps
we can take to minimize risk.
Those with healthier diets
in general, seem to suffer
less serious courses, but this appears
to be an indirect benefit
of lower rates of obesity
and pre-existing medical conditions.
I mean, that’s great, but is there any diet
that may have direct effects
on the course of disease
or susceptibility
to infection in the first place?
Well, plant-based diets
have been shown to decrease
the risk of suffering from other
respiratory infections—in fact,
plant-based seminaries
during the pandemic of 1918
appeared to have been
relatively spared.
Why might a plant-based diet help?
Vegetable nitrates concentrated
in dark green leafy vegetables
can be used to make nitric oxide,
which is part of our lungs’ first line
of defense against infection.
There are also polyphenol
phytonutrients in plants
that may directly inhibit
viral infection.
Then there are beneficial
effects on our microbiome,
which plays a key role in our
system-wide immune function.
Fiber-containing foods facilitate
more of a symbiotic relationship
with our gut bugs, whereas
processed junk and animal foods
can have the opposite,
dysbiotic effect.
Fiber, concentrated
in whole plant foods,
is the single most anti-inflammatory
food component,
whereas saturated fat, concentrated
in meat, dairy, and junk,
is the most pro-inflammatory
food component.
And so, no surprise
those consuming
more pro-inflammatory diets
were at greater risk
of suffering a severe course,
and of getting COVID-19
in the first place,
up to nearly
twelve times the odds,
even after taking
into account body weight,
diabetes, and blood pressure.
But this study only covered
60 COVID patients.
How about 11,000 COVID patients?
Diet-associated
inﬂammation increased
the risk of getting
COVID-19 infection,
suffering a severe course
and dying from the disease.
Might this help explain
why the COVID death rates
were a hundred times
lower in Africa?
Can a plant-based diet
help mitigate
COVID-19? Let’s find out.
In this study of COVID-19 illness
severity in the elderly
in relation to vegetarian versus
non-vegetarian diets, statistically,
the nonvegetarians had up to
like 20 times the odds
of suffering a critically
severe course of COVID,
but that was based
on only nine vegetarians.
Now here, a study of thousands
of front-line healthcare workers
across six countries found that
those eating plant-based diets
had 73 percent lower odds
of suffering a moderate
or severe course
of COVID-19,
and even combined
with pescatarians
(who eat fish but no other meat)
still had significantly lower odds.
The biggest spread was between
those eating plant-based
versus low-carb.
Compared to plant-based
healthcare workers,
those eating low carb,
high-protein diets had nearly
four times greater odds of suffering
a serious infection.
This may not seem
surprising given that many
of the underlying risk factors
for COVID-19 mortality—obesity,
heart disease, high blood pressure,
and type 2 diabetes—
can be controlled or even
reversed with a healthy enough
plant-based diet and lifestyle.
But the apparent plant-based
protection went above and beyond.
The greatly reduced risk was
independent of all those conditions.
The researchers suggest
that a "healthy diet
rich in nutrient-dense foods
may be considered for protection
against severe COVID-19."
The one food group most associated
with lower symptom severity
in one outpatient study was legumes,
followed by grains, the top sources
of dietary fiber.
The investigators suggest
that the anti-inflammatory effects
of the short-chain fatty acids
released by our fiber-feeding
good gut bugs may explain
the connection.
The healthcare worker study
enrolled a few thousand people,
but Harvard researchers
collected data
from nearly 600,000 participants
using a plant-based diet
scoring system where you get
points for eating healthy plant foods,
but points deducted for meat,
eggs, junk, and dairy.
And indeed those scoring
higher not only had
a significantly lower risk of suffering
a severe course of COVID-19,
but also a significantly lower risk
of getting infected
in the first place.
And again, this was after taking
comorbidities into account,
alongside nondietary risk factors
such as exercise and smoking.
The bottom line: "the best
available evidence suggests
that plant-based diets are beneﬁcial
in directly reducing the risk
of severe COVID-19 symptoms
and the risk of infection,"
even independent of other
health-related factors.
A more Mediterranean-style
diet may reduce the risk
of infection by 22 percent,
while an even more
plant-based diet
may cut infection risk in half.
For dealing with long COVID, a plant-
based diet has been suggested
based on the abundance of data
showing positive associations
of plant-based diets
with improved immune function,
neurotransmitter balance, pain
and inﬂammation reduction,
improved sleep, and mental health.
So, in terms of lifestyle adjustments
in long-COVID management,
"large-scale promotion
of plant-based eating"
may have the potential to improve
physical and mental impacts,
but this has yet
to be put to the test.
There was a study that suggested
that those who eat more vegetables
are less likely to end up depressed,
and those who eat more nuts,
beans, and whole grains
may end up less depressed, anxious,
and stressed after COVID-19,
whereas stress levels were
correlated with higher meat intake.
But the only interventional
studies are like this,
showing a detrimental impact
on high-fat high-sugar diets,
but that’s in Syrian hamsters,
though there are definitely
some unhappy hamster lungs
on the crappy diet.
All in all, adopting
a healthy plant-based diet
may be a powerful tool to decrease
the risk of severe COVID-19
and should be promoted as
a public health safety measure.
And what are the side-effects?
A delay in aging
and decreased disease.
Maybe this is the booster we need.
After all, if real effort
had gone into encouraging
and incentivizing healthier diets
and lifestyles,
we would not only have saved
many more lives from COVID-19,
but we would also reduce
future mortality
from all major causes of death.
Finally today,
I share with you some research
about how to reform the food system
before it’s too late.
Infectious diseases are emerging
globally at an unprecedented rate.
Literally hundreds of new pathogens
have emerged and re-remerged
over the last few decades and
what we eat is responsible
for most of the new diseases that
have jumped from animals to humans.
In response to the torrent of emerging
zoonotic or animal-to-human diseases,
three of the world’s leading authorities—
the World Health Organization,
the Food and Agriculture Organization
of the United Nations,
and the World Organization
for Animal Health,
held a joint consultation to
determine the key underlying causes.
First on their list was the “Increasing
demand for animal protein.”
The greatest swords of Damocles dangling
are the H5 and H7 bird flu viruses
blanketing much of the earth.
A bird flu pandemic could be devastating
given their current upwards of
Ebola-like flip-of-the-coin death rates.
Given that the emergence of
these deadly bird flu viruses,
H5N1 and H7N9 are “linked to
intensification of the poultry sector,”
there have been calls for the
“de-industrialization of animal production,”
for example, as suggested
here in the Annals of the
New York Academy of Sciences,
“replacing large industrial units
with smaller farms with
lower stocking densities,”
potentially resulting in less stress,
less disease susceptibility,
less intense infectious contact,
and smaller infectious loads.
Maybe they’re the ones that could
use a little social distancing.
The American Public Health Association,
the largest and oldest association
of public health professionals in
the world, has called for a moratorium
on factory farming for
nearly two decades now.
Maybe COVID-19 is the dry run we
needed, the fire drill to awake us
from our complacency and reform
the food system before it’s too late.
But if, as the Food and Agriculture
Organization of the United Nations
visualized it, the next
pandemic starts with
“increased demand for poultry
products,” before ending up
with human-to-human transmission,
maybe we need to move beyond
just giving these animals
some more breathing room.
It is curious, therefore,
given the pandemic threat,
that changing the way
humans treat animals—
most basically, ceasing to
eat them or, at the very least,
radically limiting the quantity
of them that are eaten—
is largely off the radar as a
significant preventive measure.
Such a change, if sufficiently
adopted or imposed,
could still reduce the chances
of the much-feared influenza epidemic.
It would be even more likely to prevent
unknown future diseases that,
in the absence of this change,
may result from farming animals
intensively and killing them for food.
Yet, humanity doesn’t
even consider this option.
However, thanks to food
innovations, this may be changing.
Have you looked in the dairy
case at the supermarket lately?
Some of America’s largest
dairy producers have recently
filed for bankruptcy due to the
constellation of new consumer choices.
I was peripherally involved in the
largest meat recall in human history.
Remember the footage of
the cows getting forklifted?
A hidden-camera investigation at
a California slaughter plant
for “spent” dairy cows led to a
recall of nearly 150 million pounds
of beef for violations of food
safety rules meant to protect
the public from mad cow disease.
Downed dairy cows, too sick to even walk,
were being dragged to
slaughter with chains
into the federal school lunch program.
You don’t have to worry about
contaminated cattle brains...
in your oatmilk, though.
Plant-based milks are a no-brainer.
But, you can see what I’m saying.
Yes, you can pass public
health regulations to stop
the cannibalistic feeding of
slaughterhouse waste to dairy cows
—or you can just provide the public
better alternatives and let
the market eliminate the risk entirely
because there’s no prions in plants.
HIV/AIDS likely arose from
people slaughtering primates.
30 million people wouldn’t
be dead right now
if we were eating meals from
bushes instead of bushmeat.
We can’t get coronaviruses
from cauliflower.
There is no flu in falafel
production no matter
how tightly you crowd the balls together.
What I'm saying, is our food choices
don’t just affect our personal
health, but our global health.
Not just in terms of climate change,
but in terms of stifling pandemic risk.
There's been a tremendous surge in
interest in diversified protein sources,
given the increasing consensus
that reduced meat consumption
is critical for addressing
both the climate crisis
and our burgeoning epidemics
of lifestyle diseases.
Eating less meat may not
only help save the world,
but could help prevent the loss of
more than ten million
human lives a year.
To their credit, in 2016, the
Chinese government recommended
its citizens cut their meat
consumption in half in part
to reduce their growing
rates of chronic disease.
A completely plant-based
diet might reap $30 trillion
from the health benefits alone,
and that would be just
from the lowered rates of chronic
diseases like cancer, heart disease,
type 2 diabetes, not even factoring in
the decreased catastrophic pandemic risk.
What we eat doesn’t just
affect our personal health,
but our global health in
more ways than one.
Making healthier choices could also help
mediate the next coronavirus epidemic,
not only at the source by
sidestepping wet markets,
but by also decreasing the rates
of comorbidities found to increase
the risk in all the deadly coronaviruses:
SARS, MERS, and COVID-19.
Consider the underlying risk factors
for COVID-19 severity and death—
obesity, heart disease,
hypertension, type 2 diabetes
and chronic pulmonary disease.
In virtually all studies, vegetable
protein is superior to animal protein
in terms of lower rates of heart
disease, and type 2 diabetes
and lower blood pressure
than animal protein.
The same diet that can help
you survive this pandemic
can also help prevent the next.
So instead of propping up the
meat industry to the tune
a 100 million taxpayer dollars
a month, and forcing meat plants
to stay open,
pandemic proof your diet.
Thankfully, expanded options are
now hitting the meat case as well.
No longer a niche market for
vegetarians, major meat producers
have started blending in vegetable
proteins to make hybrid meat products
like Perdue’s chicken plus nuggets
or Tyson’s “Whole Blends” sausage links.
Smithfield, the world’s
largest pork producer,
recently debuted an entire line
of plant-based products.
Hormel, has a new plant-based line
too, the purveyors of SPAM…
now believe in the power of plants.
Check out this headline
from a few weeks ago:
“KFC to roll out Cargill’s plant‐
based chicken across China.”
Talk about a cultural revolution.
And, we’re not talking
about Tofurkey.
Cargill is America’s largest
private corporation,
and one of the biggest meat
packers in the world.
How many fewer curly-tailed
viral mixing vessels are there now
that Dunkin’ Donuts has a
meat-free breakfast sausage?
How many fewer hens are packed beak-
to-beak now that egg-free mayo
has taken the sandwich
spread sector by a storm?
Quorn, a brand of meat-free meat
made from the mushroom kingdom,
opened a single facility
that can produce the meat
equivalent of twenty
million chickens per year.
These products may not be the
healthiest from a personal standpoint—
a doughnut sandwich without
pork is still a doughnut sandwich—
but hey, swap in an egg-free
omelette from Tim Hortons
and from a pandemic standpoint?
Zero risk.
Doesn’t necessarily have
to be plants, though.
Researchers are seeking
alternative protein sources everywhere.
Can’t think of any possible
alternative to cow’s milk?
How about cockroach milk?
Could be healthier than cow’s
milk, and hey no lactose,
no dairy allergy problems.
An important alternative.
I mean I can’t imagine anything
else you can make milk out of.
And gluten-free too!
The only downside,
evidently, was the flavor,
but the researchers—
perhaps funded by Big Bug?—
chalked this up to the fact that the
judges knew there were cockroaches
in the bread; and so,
they were all just biased.
Hmmm... I think I’ll stick with the plants.
But if you’re like: “you’ll
have to pry that pork chop
from my cold, dead hands,”
we may be able to have
our meat and eat it too.
An even more innovative
approach to pandemic prevention
was suggested by
Winston Churchill in 1932.
In an article in Popular
Mechanics entitled
“Fifty Years Hence,”
he predicted that
“We shall escape the
absurdity of growing
a whole chicken in order
to eat the breast or wing,
by growing these parts separately
under a suitable medium.”
And indeed, the prediction
is becoming a reality.
Instead of taking a cutting from
a plant and growing vegetables
you’re taking a sample from
an animal and growing meat.
Potentially lots of meat, like maybe
a billion pounds from a single sample.
Indeed, in terms of efficiency,
growing meat straight from muscle cells
could reduce greenhouse gas emissions
and water use by as much as 96%,
and lower land use by as much as 99%,
but when you factor in pandemic risk,
the benefits to human health
of a slaughter-free harvest
could arguably rival
those to planetary health.
Food safety has been
considered the primary
human health benefit
of such an approach.
There has been a six-fold
increase in food poisoning
over the last few decades, sickening
tens of millions of Americans every year,
and contaminated meats and animal
products are the most common cause.
So, when the cultivated meat industry
calls its product “clean meat,”
that’s not just a nod to clean energy.
Food-poisoning pathogens
like E. coli, Campylobacter,
and Salmonella are
due to fecal residue,
traces of which are found on most
poultry sampled in the United States
and about half of retail
ground beef and pork chops.
They’re intestinal bugs; so, you
don’t have to worry about them
if you’re producing meat
without intestines.
You don’t have to cook the crap out of
meat, if there’s no crap to begin with,
just like you don’t have to worry
about brewing up new respiratory viruses
that could kill millions of people if
you’re making meat without the lungs.
“A culinary choice in south China
led to a fatal infection in Hong Kong,
and subsequently to 8000 cases of
severe acute respiratory syndrome (SARS),
and nearly 1000 deaths in 30
countries on six continents.”
If only we had learned our lesson then.
We may be one bushmeat meal away
from the next HIV, one
pangolin plate away
from the next killer coronavirus,
and one factory farm away
from the next deadly flu.
Tragically, it may take a
pandemic with a virus
like H5N1 before the world realizes
the true cost of cheap chicken.
We would love it if you could
share with us your stories
about reinventing your health
through evidence-based nutrition.
Go to nutritionfacts.org/testimonials.
We may share it on our social
media to help inspire others.
To see any graphs, charts, graphics,
images, or studies mentioned here,
go to the Nutrition Facts
Podcast landing page.
There you’ll find all the
detailed information you need –
plus, links to all of the sources
we cite for each of these topics.
My last two books were
“How to Survive a Pandemic”
and my “How Not to Diet Cookbook”.
Get ready this year for the
launch of “How Not to Age”.
And, of course, all the proceeds
I receive from the sales
of all my books goes
directly to charity.
NutritionFacts.org is a nonprofit,
science-based public service,
where you can sign up
for free daily updates
on the latest in nutrition research
with bite-sized videos and articles
uploaded nearly every day.
Everything on the
website is free.
There’s no ads, no
corporate sponsorships,
no kickbacks.
It’s strictly non-commercial.
I’m not selling anything.
I just put it up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to
my grandmother,
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.